Institutes of Religion and Health Records
Institutes of Religion and Health Records
1951-1975
Institutes of Religion and Health.
6.0 linear ft.
The Institutes of Religion and Health was formed by the merger of the Academy of Religion and Mental Health, and the American Foundation of Religion and Psychiatry, with its Blanton-Peale Graduate Institute. The merger combined the resources of two long established and widely known interfaith, interracial, interdisciplinary, nonprofit, tax-exempt agencies serving human health and well-being. Collection comprises organizational records including general files, correspondence, financial records (balance sheets, budgets), and printed material (annual reports, bulletins, newsletters).
149074
Biographical History
The Institutes of Religion and Health was formed by the merger of the Academy of Religion and Mental Health and the American Foundation of Religion and Psychiatry, with its Blanton-Peale Graduate Institute. The merger combined the resources of two long established and widely known interfaith, interracial, interdisciplinary, nonprofit, tax-exempt agencies serving human health and well-being.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Institutes of Religion and Health Records comprises organizational records including general files, correspondence, financial records (balance sheets, budgets), and printed material (annual reports, bulletins, newsletters). The material is divided into four series.
General files contain organizational material dating from 1951 when the Institutes were first incorporated as the American Foundation of Religion and Psychiatry. This series also contains materials relating to the three main functions of the Institutes -- a mental health clinic, pastoral counseling training, and social research.
Correspondence includes Director's and two other individuals (Dr. Maxfield, Mr. C. W. Stone) and correspondence with the New York City Mental Health Board as well as nearly ten years of general correspondence.
Financial papers comprises balance sheets, budgets, financial forecasts and reports, financial statements, and monthly balance sheets.
Printed material includes fliers, brochures, newsletters, public relations, and issues of The Pastoral Counselor and Thought and Worship.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically by type or title; subseries of correspondence are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and Philosophy; Science and medicine; Blanton, Smiley, 1882-1966.; Peale, Norman Vincent, 1898-1993.; Academy of Religion and Mental Health.; American Foundation of Religion and Psychiatry.; Blanton-Peale Graduate Institute.; Institutes of Religion and Health (New York, N.Y.), Archives.; Medical social work.; Medicine, Religious aspects.; Mental health, Religious aspects.; Mental health counseling.; Pastoral counseling.; Psychiatry and religion.; Social service, United States.; Annual reports.; Balance sheets.; Budgets.; Bulletins.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- General files
  - Board meeting minutes
    - Charter members, 1951-1958 (Box 1)
    - Directors
      - 1954-1975, 29 folders (Box 1)
      - Staff conferences (Box 1)
    - Governors, 1959-1964; 1966-1970; 9 folders (Box 1)
    - Joint board meetings
      - Directors and Governors, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
      - Directors and Governors, 1965 (Box 1)
      - Directors and Governors, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
      - Directors, Governors and Trustees, 1971; 1974 (Box 1)
      - Directors, Trustees, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Trustees, 1969; 1973 (Box 1)
  - Committee meeting minutes
    - Administrative
      - 1956-1964, 6 folders (Box 1)
      - 1964-1967, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Admissions, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Child Guidance (Box 2)
    - Clinic (Box 2)
    - Clinical methods (Box 2)
    - Clinical services
      - 1958-1964, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - General file (Box 2)
    - Curriculum (Box 2)
    - Editorial ( The Pastoral Counselor) (Box 2)
    - Education, 4 May 1964 (Box 2)
    - Ethical practices (Box 2)
    - Executive
      - 1955-1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1960-1968, 21 folders (Box 2)
      - 1972-1975 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 2)
    - Finance
      - 1963 (Box 2)
      - 1965, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Long Range Planning and Endowment (Box 3)
    - Marriage Guidance (Box 3)
    - Policy and Personnel, 1965-1966; 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Supervision and Private Practice (Box 3)
  - Functions
    - Bureau of Applied Social Research
      - Correspondence and information, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Proposal for research (Box 3)
      - Research advisory committee (Box 3)
      - Statistics and information (Box 3)
    - Counseling service (clinic)
      - Clinic problem chart (Box 3)
      - Clinical brochure draft (Box 3)
      - Clinical services (Box 3)
      - Continuous case conference (Box 3)
      - Group therapy
        - General (Box 3)
        - C.W. Kew, 1960 (Box 3)
      - Healing Services, C.W. Kew (Box 3)
      - National Institute of Mental Health, application forms (Box 3)
    - Pastoral counseling training
      - Accreditation committee (Box 3)
      - Case conferences (Box 3)
      - Child guidance manual (Box 3)
      - Guideposts (Box 3)
      - Marriage counseling seminar (Box 3)
      - Marriage counseling training, correspondence, notes (Box 3)
      - Scholarships and fellowships (Box 3)
      - Staff articles (Box 3)
      - Staff conferences (Box 3)
      - Staff make-up charts (Box 3)
      - Summer seminars (Box 3)
      - Training calendar, 1957-1964; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - History and politics
    - Foundation history (Box 4)
    - Original papers (Box 4)
    - Policies (Box 4)
    - The role of religion in AFRAP, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "A Statement" (draft) (Box 4)
  - Procedures and regulations
    - Administrative procedures (Box 4)
    - Policies and procedures manual (draft), 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Proposed pension plan (Box 4)
    - Staff - clerical regulations (Box 4)
  - Spring planning conference
    - 1961-1966, 6 folders (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  - Director's (Box 4)
  - Dr. Maxfield / Mr. C. W. Stone, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1967; 8 folders (Box 4)
  - New York City Mental Health Board, 1955-1965; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Speaking engagement, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Financial material
  - Balance sheets, 1966-1967; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Budgets, 1960-1967; 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Departmental budget proposals (Box 5)
  - Financial forecasts (Box 5)
  - Financial reports, 1962-1966; 1968; 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Financial statements (Box 5)
  - Monthly balance sheets, 1962-1965; 4 folders (Box 5)
- Printed material
  - Annual reports, 1955-1965; 1967-1970; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Bulletin (Box 5)
  - Bureau of Social Research brochures (Box 6)
  - Fliers (Box 6)
  - Healing service brochures (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - News bulletins (Box 6)
  - Newsletters (Box 6)
  - The Pastoral Counselor (Box 6)
  - Public relations packet (Box 6)
  - Reprints: staff research (Box 6)
  - Summer seminar brochures (Box 6)
  - Thought and Worship (Box 6)
  - Training brochures (Box 6)
  - Weekly staff letter, 3 folders (Box 6)